<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode type="Sink" icon="./xlsappender.png">
	<name>XLS Appender</name>

	<shortDescription>
		Saves a datatable into a spreadsheet.
	</shortDescription>

	<fullDescription>
		<intro>
			This node writes out the datatable coming through its input
			port into a spreadsheet and appends it to an existing workbook.
            If no workbook is present a new one will be created. The files can
            be read then with other applications like Microsoft Excel, for
			example. The maximum number of columns held by a spreadsheet
			is 256 (all additional columns in the datatable are
			truncated). If the input datatable has more than 65536 rows
			it is split into multiple spreadsheets (all stored in the
			created workbook).
		</intro>
		<option name="Output file location">
			Enter a valid file name. You can also choose a previously
			selected file from the drop-down list, or select a file from
			the &quot;Browse...&quot; dialog.
		</option>
        <option name="Abort if file does not exist">
            Abort the execution if the XLS file does not exist. If this option
            is not selected a new file will be created.
        </option>
        <option name="Abort if sheet already exists">
            If a sheet with the same name does already exist, then the execution
            will fail. If this option is not selected the old sheet will be
            replaced by the new one.
        </option>
        <option name="Sheet name">
            Name of the sheet that will be created. If left empty, the name of
            the input table will be used.
        </option>
		<option name="Write column header">
			If checked, the column names are written out in the first
			row of the spreadsheet.
		</option>
		<option name="Write row ID">
			If checked, the row IDs are added to the output, in the
			first column of the spreadsheet.
		</option>
		<option name="Missing Value Pattern">
			Enter a pattern that is set for missing data values. If not
			specified, the corresponding datacell of the spreadsheet
			stays empty.
		</option>
        <option name="Open file after execution">
            Opens the file after it has been successfully written. The file will
            be opened in the default application of the system. This might not
            be supported by every system.
        </option>
        <option name="Exclude/Include columns">
            Select the columns that will be written in the XLS file. If the
            columns in the input table should change, they will automatically be
            excluded.
        </option>
	</fullDescription>

	<ports>
		<inPort index="0" name="Input table">
			The Datatable to write out.
		</inPort>
	</ports>
</knimeNode>


