<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE knimeNode PUBLIC "-//UNIKN//DTD KNIME Node 2.0//EN" "http://www.knime.org/Node.dtd">
<knimeNode type="Sink" icon="./xlswriter.png">
	<name>XLS Writer</name>

	<shortDescription>
		Saves a datatable into a spreadsheet.
	</shortDescription>

	<fullDescription>
		<intro>
			This node writes out the datatable coming through its input
			port into a spreadsheet of a workbook. The files can be read
			then with other applications like Microsoft Excel, for
			example. The maximum number of columns held by a spreadsheet
			is 256 (all additional columns in the datatable are
			truncated). If the input datatable has more than 65536 rows
			it is split into multiple spreadsheets (all stored in the
			created workbook).
		</intro>
		<option name="Output file location">
			Enter a valid file name. You can also choose a previously
			selected file from the drop-down list, or select a file from
			the &quot;Browse...&quot; dialog.
		</option>
        <option name="Overwrite existing file"> If checked, the output 
            file will be overridden if it exists. If unchecked, the node will fail during 
            execution in order to retain the original file and to avoid unintentional 
            overwrite. </option>
        <option name="Open file after execution">
            Opens the file after it has been successfully written. The file will
            be opened in the default application of the system. This might not
            be supported by every system.
        </option>
        <option name="Sheet name">
            Name of the sheet that will be created. If left empty, the name of
            the input table will be used.
        </option>
		<option name="Write column header">
			If checked, the column names are written out in the first
			row of the spreadsheet.
		</option>
		<option name="Write row ID">
			If checked, the row IDs are added to the output, in the
			first column of the spreadsheet.
		</option>
		<option name="Missing Value Pattern">
			Enter a pattern that is set for missing data values. If not
			specified, the corresponding datacell of the spreadsheet
			stays empty.
		</option>
		<option name="Autosize columns">
			Fits the columns width to the content.
		</option>
		<option name="Portrait/Landscape">
			Sets the print format to portrait or landscape.
		</option>
		<option name="Paper size">
			Sets the paper size in the print setup.
		</option>
        <option name="Exclude/Include columns">
            Select the columns that will be written in the XLS file. If the
            columns in the input table should change, they will automatically be
            excluded.
        </option>
	</fullDescription>

	<ports>
		<inPort index="0" name="Input table">
			The Datatable to write out.
		</inPort>
	</ports>
</knimeNode>


