<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<knimeNode type="Sink" icon="./xlsappender.png"
	xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v3.6"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v3.6 http://knime.org/node/v3.6.xsd">
	<name>Excel Sheet Appender (XLS)</name>

	<shortDescription>
		Appends a data table to an existing workbook.
	</shortDescription>

	<fullDescription>
		<intro>
			<p>This node writes the input data table into a spreadsheet and appends it to an existing workbook.
            If no workbook is present, a new one will be created. The files can then be read with other
            applications such as Microsoft Excel.</p>
            <p>The node supports three formats chosen by file extension:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    .xls format: This is the file format which was used by default up until Excel 2003. The maximum
                    number of columns held by a spreadsheet of this format is 256 (all additional columns in the data
                    table are truncated). If the input data table has more than 65536 rows, it is split into multiple
                    spreadsheets (all stored in the created workbook).
                </li>
                <li>
                    .xlsx format: The Office Open XML format is the file format used by default from Excel 2007 onwards.
                </li>
	 			<li>
	 				.xlsm format: This node can append data to macro-enabled workbooks, however, new workbooks cannot 
	 				be created this way.
				</li>
            </ul>
            </p>
            <p>Specifying
            a remote URL as the destination location will force the node to overwrite this file as it is not
            possible to determine whether this location already exists. If no extension is specified, the
            file will be written in the .xlsx format.</p>
		</intro>
		<option name="Output location">
			Enter a valid file name or URL. You can also choose a previously
			selected location from the drop-down list, or select a file from
			the &quot;Browse...&quot; dialog.
		</option>
        <option name="Abort if file does not exist">
            Aborts the execution if the specified file does not exist. If this option
            is not selected, a new file will be created.
        </option>
        <option name="Abort if sheet already exists">
            If a sheet with the same name does already exist, then the execution
            will fail. If this option is not selected, the old sheet will be
            replaced by the new one.
        </option>
        <option name="Open file after execution">
            Opens the file after it has been successfully created. The file will
            be opened in the default application of the system. This might not
            be supported by every system.
        </option>
        <option name="Sheet name">
            Name of the sheet that will be created. If left empty, the name of
            the input table will be used.
        </option>
		<option name="Write column header">
			If checked, the column names are written out in the first
			row of the spreadsheet.
		</option>
		<option name="Write row ID">
			If checked, the row IDs are added to the output, in the
			first column of the spreadsheet.
		</option>
        <option name="Evaluate Formulas on write">
            If checked, all formulas in the file will be evaluated after the sheet has been written. This is useful
            if other sheets in the file refer to the data just written and their content needs updating. 
        </option>
		<option name="Missing Value Pattern">
			Enter a pattern that is used for missing data values. If not
			specified, the corresponding data cell of the spreadsheet
			stays empty.
		</option>
		<option name="Autosize columns">
			Fits each column's width to its content.
		</option>
		<option name="Portrait/Landscape">
			Sets the print format to portrait or landscape.
		</option>
		<option name="Paper size">
			Sets the paper size in the print setup.
		</option>
        <option name="Exclude/Include columns">
            Select the columns that will be appended to the file. If the
            columns in the input table change, they will automatically be
            excluded.
        </option>
	</fullDescription>

	<ports>
		<inPort index="0" name="Input table">
			The data table to write out.
		</inPort>
	</ports>
</knimeNode>


