<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<knimeNode icon="./xlswriter.png" type="Sink"
	xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v3.6"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v3.6 http://knime.org/node/v3.6.xsd">
    <name>Excel Writer (XLS)</name>
    <shortDescription> Saves a data table into a new workbook. 
    </shortDescription>
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
            <p> This node writes the input data table into a spreadsheet of a workbook. The files can then be read with
                other applications such as Microsoft Excel.
            </p>
            <p>The node supports two formats chosen by file extension:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    .xls format: This is the file format which was used by default up until Excel 2003. The maximum
                    number of columns held by a spreadsheet of this format is 256 (all additional columns in the data
                    table are truncated). If the input data table has more than 65536 rows, it is split into multiple
                    spreadsheets (all stored in the created workbook).
                </li>
                <li>
                    .xlsx format: The Office Open XML format is the file format used by default from Excel 2007 onwards.
                </li>
            </ul>
            </p>
	        <p>This nodes does not support writing in the 'xlsm' format.</p>
            <p>Specifying a remote URL as the destination location will force the node to overwrite this file as it is 
            not possible to determine whether this location already exists. If no extension is specified, the
            file will be written in the .xlsx format.</p>
        </intro>
        <option name="Output location"> Enter a valid file name or URL. You can also choose a previously selected 
        	location from the drop-down list, or select a file from the &quot;Browse...&quot; dialog.
        </option>
        <option name="Overwrite existing file"> Existing files will be overwritten if this option is enabled. Otherwise 
        	the node will fail during execution to retain the original file and to avoid unintentional overwrite. 
        	Remote locations will always be overwritten.
        </option>
        <option name="Open file after execution"> 
            Opens the file after it has been successfully created. The file will be opened in the default application 
            of the system. This might not be supported by every system and is not available for remote locations.
        </option>
        <option name="Sheet name"> Name of the sheet that will be created. If left empty, the name of the input table 
        	will be used.
        </option>
        <option name="Write column header"> If checked, the column names are written out in the first row of the 
        	spreadsheet.
        </option>
        <option name="Write row ID"> If checked, the row IDs are added to the output, in the first column of the 
        	spreadsheet.
        </option>
        <option name="Missing Value Pattern"> Enter a pattern that is used for missing data values. If not specified, 
        	the corresponding data cell of the spreadsheet stays empty.
        </option>
        <option name="Autosize columns"> Fits each column's width to its content.
        </option>
        <option name="Portrait/Landscape"> Sets the print format to portrait or landscape.
        </option>
        <option name="Paper size"> Sets the paper size in the print setup.
        </option>
        <option name="Exclude/Include columns"> Select the columns that will be written in the file. If the columns in 
        	the input table should change, they will automatically be excluded.
        </option>
    </fullDescription>
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input table"> The data table to write out.
        </inPort>
    </ports>
</knimeNode>