<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<knimeNode xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v4.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" icon="./excel_sheet_updater.png" type="Sink" xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v4.1 http://knime.org/node/v4.1.xsd">
  <name>Excel Sheet Updater</name>
  <shortDescription>
    Updates single cells in an Excel file
  </shortDescription>
  <fullDescription>
    <intro>
      <p>
        This node updates cells in an existing Excel spreadsheet. The cell addresses and their
        new content are supplied by an input data table.
        
      </p>
      <p>
        Adding additional table input ports allows to update multiple
        spreadsheets in the same file.
      </p>
      <p>
        The node supports two file formats chosen by file extension:
        <ul>
          <li>
            .xls format: This is the file format which was used by default up
            until Excel 2003. The maximum number of columns
            held by a spreadsheet of this format is 256 (address IV) and the
            maximum number of rows is 65536.
          </li>
          <li>
            .xlsx format: The Office Open XML format is the file format used by
            default from Excel 2007 onwards.
            The maximum number of columns held by a spreadsheet of this format
            is 16384 (address XFD) and the maximum number of rows is 1048576.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>
        Each input table must have one column which contains the addresses (or
        coordinates) of the sheet cells which should be updated. This column has
        to have a string-compatible type and must contain
        Excel cell addresses as strings, e.g. "A5", "E96" or "OZ23124".
      </p>
      <p>
        The rest of the cells in a table row determine which value should be
        written. Each row must only contain at most one non-missing value that
        contains the value which should be written into the specified Excel cell.
        The type of the table row is used as the Excel type so a number column
        should be used to write numbers etc.
      </p>
      <p>
        The node will write a blank cell or the string specified in "Replace
        missing values by" if all cells except for the address cell in a row are
        missing.
      </p>
      <p>
        The formatting of existing cells, rows and columns in the Excel sheet will be preserved.
      </p>
      <p>
        In the following a <b>?</b> stands for a missing value.
        This example table would write the string "Ok" to Excel cell A5 and the
        number "50" to cell E96. The cell OZ23124 will be cleared if no
        alternate missing value is defined.
      </p>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <th>Address</th>
            <th>String</th>
            <th>Integer</th>
            <th>Date</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>A5</td>
            <td>Ok</td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>E96</td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
            <td>50</td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>OZ23124</td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
            <td><b>?</b></td>
          </tr>
        </table>
        <p>
          <i>This node can access a variety of different</i>
          <a href="https://docs.knime.com/2021-06/analytics_platform_file_handling_guide/index.html#analytics-platform-file-systems"><i>file systems.</i></a>
          <i>More information about file handling in KNIME can be found in the official</i>
          <a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/analytics_platform_file_handling_guide/index.html"><i>File Handling Guide.</i></a>
        </p>
      </intro>
      <option name="Read from">
        Select a file system which stores the data you want to read from and
        potentially update. There are four default file system options to
        choose from:
        <br />
        <ul>
          <li>
            <i>Local File System:</i>
            Allows you to select a file/folder from your
            local system.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Mountpoint:</i>
            Allows you to read from a mountpoint.
            When selected, a new drop-down menu appears to choose the
            mountpoint. Unconnected mountpoints are greyed out but can
            still be selected (note that browsing is disabled in this case).
            Go to the KNIME Explorer and connect to the mountpoint to enable
            browsing. A mountpoint is displayed in red if it was
            previously selected but is no longer available. You won't be
            able to save the dialog as long as you don't select a valid, i.e.
            known mountpoint.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Relative to:</i>
            Allows you to choose whether to resolve the path
            relative to the current mountpoint, current workflow or the
            current workflow's data area. When selected a new drop-down
            menu appears to choose which of the three options to use.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Custom/KNIME URL:</i>
            Allows to specify a URL (e.g. file://, http:// or knime://
            protocol).
            When selected, a spinner appears that allows you to specify
            the desired connection and read timeout in milliseconds. In
            case it takes longer to connect to the host / read the file,
            the node fails to execute. Browsing is disabled for this
            option.
          </li>
        </ul>
        To read from other file systems, click on
        <b>...</b>
        in the bottom left corner of the node icon followed by
        <i>Add File System Connection port.</i>
        Afterwards, connect the desired file system connector
        node to the newly added input port. The file system
        connection will then be shown in the drop-down menu.
        It is greyed out if the file system is not connected in
        which case you have to (re)execute the connector node first.
        Note: The default file systems listed above can't be
        selected if a file system is provided via the input port.
      </option>
      <option name="File/URL">
        Enter a URL when writing to
        <i>
          Custom/KNIME URL,
        </i>
        otherwise enter a path to a file. The
        required syntax of a path depends on the chosen file system,
        such as "C:\path\to\file" (Local File System on
        Windows) or "/path/to/file" (Local File System
        on Linux/MacOS and Mountpoint). For file systems connected via
        input port, the node description of the
        respective connector node describes the required path format.
        You can also choose a previously selected file from the
        drop-down list, or select a location from the
        "Browse..." dialog. Note that browsing is
        disabled in some cases:
        <ul>
          <li>
            <i>Custom/KNIME URL:</i>
            Browsing is always disabled.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Mountpoint:</i>
            Browsing is disabled if the selected mountpoint isn't
            connected.
            Go to the KNIME Explorer and connect to the mountpoint
            to enable browsing.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>File systems provided via input port:</i>
            Browsing is disabled if the connector node hasn't
            been executed since the workflow has been opened.
            (Re)execute the connector node to enable browsing.
          </li>
        </ul>
        <i>
          The location can be exposed as or automatically set
          via a
        </i>
        <a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/analytics_platform_file_handling_guide/index.html#path">
          <i>path flow variable.</i>
        </a>
      </option>
      <option name="Create a new file">
        If this option is selected, create a copy of the
        original file which is updated instead of the original
        file. The newly created file must have the same file
        type as the original file.
      </option>
      <option name="Write to">
        Provide the path to new file that should be used.
        This has the same file system and file options
        as "Read from".
      </option>
      <option name="Create missing folders">
        Select if the folders of the selected output location
        should be created when they do not already exist. If this
        option is unchecked, the node will fail if a folder does
        not exist.
      </option>
      <option name="If exists">
        Specify the behavior of the node in case the output file
        already exists.
        <ul>
          <li>
            <i>Overwrite:</i>
            Will replace any existing file.
          </li>
          <li>
            <i>Fail:</i>
            Will issue an error during the node's execution
            (to prevent unintentional overwrite).
          </li>
        </ul>
      </option>
      <option name="Excel sheet">
        Specify which sheet should be update by the
        corresponding input table.
      </option>
      <option name="Based on address column">
        Select the name of the column which contains the
        addresses (or coordinates) of the cells which
        should be updated.
      </option>
      <option name="Replaces missing values by">
        If selected, the node will write the specified value
        as a string to the address if only missing values
        are found in that row, otherwise a blank cell is created.
      </option>
      <option name="Evaluate formulas">
        If checked, all formulas in the file will be
        evaluated after the sheet's updates have been
        performed. This is useful if values that are
        used in formulas in the sheets have been updated.
      </option>
    </fullDescription>
    <ports>
      <inPort index="0" name="Input table">
        The data table which contains the update data.
      </inPort>
      <dynInPort insert-before="0" name="File system connection" group-identifier="File System Connection">
        The file system connection.
      </dynInPort>
      <dynInPort insert-before="1" name="Additional input tables" group-identifier="Sheet Input Ports">
        Additional data tables which contain update data.
      </dynInPort>
    </ports>
  </knimeNode>
