<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<knimeNode icon="./excel_writer.png" type="Sink"
	 xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v4.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
	 xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v4.1 http://knime.org/node/v4.1.xsd">
    <name>Excel Writer</name>
    <shortDescription> Writes data tables to an Excel file.
    </shortDescription>
    <fullDescription>
        <intro>
            <p><i>This node supports the
            </i><a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/analytics_platform_file_handling_guide/index.html#path"><i>path flow variable.</i></a>
            <i> For further information about file handling in general see the
            </i><a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/analytics_platform_file_handling_guide/index.html"><i>File Handling Guide.</i></a><br/></p>
            
            <p> This node writes the input data table into a spreadsheet of an Excel file. The files can then
                be read with other applications such as Microsoft Excel.
                <br/>
                Adding additional sheet input ports allows to write multiple spreadsheets to the same file. Furthermore,
                it is also possible to append sheets to an already existing excel file by selecting the <i>append</i>
                option.
            </p>
            <p>The node supports two formats chosen by file extension:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    .xls format: This is the file format which was used by default up until Excel 2003. The maximum
                    number of columns and rows held by a spreadsheet of this format is
                    256 and 65536 respectively.
                </li>
                <li>
                    .xlsx format: The Office Open XML format is the file format used by default from Excel 2007 onwards.
                    The maximum number of columns and rows held by a spreadsheet of this
                    format is 16384 and 1048576 respectively.
                </li>
            </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                The node can create completely new files or append to/edit an existing Excel file.
                The data can be appended as a spreadsheet with a new name or appended after the last row
                of an existing spreadsheet.
            </p>
            <p>
                If the data does not fit into one sheet, it will be split into multiple chunks that are written
                to newly chosen sheet names sequentially. The new sheet names are derived form the originally
                selected sheet name by appending " (n)" to it where <i>n</i> is starting with one and increases by
                one for every sheet.<br/>
                If a sheet with that name already exists (when appending to an existing Excel file), the node will
                (according to its settings) either fail or append the remaining rows after the last row in that
                sheet as well. This can be used to append data to an Excel file without having to create a new sheet
                name once the original sheet is full by just pointing selecting the original sheet name. The data will
                be appendend to the last sheet in the name sequence. The original sheet name does not have to be changed.
            </p>
	        <p>This node does not support writing files in the '.xlsm' format, yet appending is supported.</p>
        </intro>
        
        <option name="Write to">
			Select a file system in which you want to store the file. There are four default file system options to
			choose from:
			<br />
			<ul>
				<li><i>Local File System:</i> Allows you to select a location on your
                    local system.
                </li>
                <li><i>Mountpoint:</i> Allows you to write to a mountpoint.
                	When selected, a new drop-down menu appears to choose the mountpoint.
                	Unconnected mountpoints are greyed out but can still be selected (note that browsing is disabled in this case).
                	Go to the KNIME Explorer and connect to the mountpoint to enable browsing.
                	A mountpoint is displayed in red if it was previously selected but is no longer available.
                	You won't be able to save the dialog as long as you don't select a valid, i.e. known, mountpoint.
                </li>
                <li><i>Relative to:</i> Allows you to choose whether to resolve the path
					relative to the current mountpoint, current workflow, or the current workflow's data area.
                When selected, a new drop-down menu appears to choose which of the three options to use.
                </li>
				<li><i>Custom/KNIME URL:</i> Allows to specify a URL (e.g. file://, http:// or knime:// protocol). 
                    When selected, a spinner appears that allows you to specify the desired connection and write timeout in milliseconds.
                    In case it takes longer to connect to the host / write the file, the node fails to execute.
                    Browsing is disabled for this option.
                </li>
			</ul>
			It is possible to use other file systems with this node. For this
			you have to enable the file system connection input port of this
			node
			by clicking the
			<b>...</b>
			in the bottom left corner of the node's icon and choose
			<i>Add File System Connection port</i>
			.
			<br />
			Afterwards, you can simply connect the desired connector node to this node.
			The file system connection will then be shown in the drop-down menu.
			It is greyed out if the file system is not connected, in which case you have to (re)execute the connector node first.
			Note: The default file systems listed above can't be selected if a file system is provided via the input port.
		</option>
		<option name="File/URL">
			Enter a URL when writing to <i>Custom/KNIME URL</i>, otherwise enter a path to a file. The
				required syntax of a path depends on the chosen file system, such as &quot;C:\path\to\file&quot; (Local
				File System on Windows) or  &quot;/path/to/file&quot; (Local
	            File System on Linux/MacOS and Mountpoint). For file systems connected via input port, the node
	            description of the respective connector node describes the required path format.
				You can also choose a previously selected file from the drop-down list, or select a location
				from the &quot;Browse...&quot; dialog.
				Note that browsing is disabled in some cases:
				<ul>
					<li><i>Custom/KNIME URL:</i> Browsing is always disabled.</li>
					<li><i>Mountpoint:</i> Browsing is disabled if the selected mountpoint isn't connected.
					Go to the KNIME Explorer and connect to the mountpoint to enable browsing.</li>
					<li><i>File systems provided via input port:</i>
					Browsing is disabled if the connector node hasn't been executed since the workflow has been opened.
					(Re)execute the connector node to enable browsing.</li>
				</ul>
                <i>The location can be exposed as or automatically set via a 
                </i><a href="https://docs.knime.com/latest/analytics_platform_file_handling_guide/index.html#path">
                <i>path flow variable.</i></a>
		</option>
		<option name="Create missing folders">Select if the folders of the selected output location should be 
			created if they do not already exist. If this option is unchecked, the node will fail if a folder does
			not exist.
		</option>
		<option name="If exists">
			Specify the behavior of the node in case the output file already exists.
			<ul>
				<li><i>Overwrite:</i> Will replace any existing file.
				</li>
				<li><i>Append:</i> Will append the input tables to the existent Excel file's sheets.
				</li>
				<li><i>Fail:</i> Will issue an error during the node's execution (to prevent unintentional overwrite).
				</li>
			</ul>
		</option>
        <option name="Sheet name">
            Name of the spreadsheets that will be created. The dropdown can be used
            to select a sheet name which already exists in the Excel file or a custom
            name can be entered. If "<i>If sheet exists</i>" isn't set to append, each
            sheet name must be unique. The node appends the tables in the
            order they are connected.
        </option>
        <option name="If sheet exists">
			Specify the behavior of the node in case a sheet with the entered name already exists.
            (This option is only relevant if the file append/edit option is selected.)
			<ul>
				<li><i>Overwrite:</i> Will replace any existing sheet.
				</li>
                <li><i>Append:</i> Will append the input tables after the last row of the sheets.<br/>
                <b>Note:</b> the last row is chosen according to the rows which already exist in the sheet.
                A row may appear empty but still exist because it or one of its cells contains styling information
                or was not removed by Excel after the user cleared it.
				</li>
				<li><i>Fail:</i> Will issue an error during the node's execution (to prevent unintentional overwrite).
				</li>
			</ul>
		</option>
        <option name="Write row key">
        	If checked, the row IDs are added to the output, in the first column of the spreadsheet.
        </option>
        <option name="Write column headers">
        	If checked, the column names are written out in the first row of the spreadsheet.
        </option>
        <option name="Don't write column headers if sheet exists">
            Only write the column headers if a sheet is newly created or replaced.
            This option is convenient if you have written data with the same specification
            to an existing sheet before and want to append new rows to it.
        </option>
        <option name="Replaces missing values by">
        	If selected, missing values will be replaced by the specified value, otherwise a blank cell is being created.
        </option>
        <option name="Evaluate formulas">
            If checked, all formulas in the file will be evaluated after the sheet has been written. This is useful
            if other sheets in the file refer to the data just written and their content needs updating. This option is
            only relevant if the append option is selected.
        </option>
        <option name="Autosize columns">
        	Fits each column's width to its content.
        </option>
        <option name="Portrait/Landscape">
        	Sets the print format to portrait or landscape.
        </option>
        <option name="Paper size">
        	Sets the paper size in the print setup.
        </option>
    </fullDescription>
    <ports>
        <inPort index="0" name="Input table"> The data table to write.</inPort>
        <dynInPort insert-before="0" name="File system connection" group-identifier="File System Connection"> 
            The file system connection.
        </dynInPort>
        <dynInPort insert-before="1" name="Additional input tables" group-identifier="Sheet Input Ports"> 
            Additional data table to write.
        </dynInPort>
    </ports>
</knimeNode>
